Ranjit Kumar Sahoo

DST-INSPIRE Faculty Fellow, CSIR-CCMB, Hyderabad, India

RK Sahoo is an early career researcher in the field of Ecology and Evolution. His research interest spans molecular evolution, population biology and host-Wolbachia interaction. For his current work, he uses the methods in experimental biology and molecular genetics to understand the underlying mechanisms of population recovery from a demographic bottleneck.

sahoo rk@outlook.com +91-7653912621 orcid.org/0000-0001-9445-1440

Skype: sahoo rk

Appointment

DST-INSPIRE Faculty Fellow Jan 2021-present

CSIR-CCMB, Hyderabad, India

Project: Evolution of small founding population

May 2019–Jan 2021 Post-Doctoral Research Fellow

IISER Berhampur, Odisha, India

Project: Chemical ecology of plant-insect interaction

Advisor: Dr. Bodhisatta Nandy

Education

2013 – 2018 PhD in Biological Sciences

IISER Thiruvananthapuram, Kerala, India Advisor: Dr. Ullasa Kodandaramaiah

Thesis: Evolution of host plant associations and diversification of butterflies

2009 - 2011Master of Science in Ecology and Environmental Sciences

Pondicherry University, Puducherry, India

Advisor: Dr. SM Sundarapandian

Thesis: Status assessment of Asian elephant in Dandeli-Anshi National Park, India

Score: 7.91/10.00 (CGPA)

2006 - 2009Bachelor of Science in Biotechnology

BJB Autonomous College, Utkal University, Odisha, India

Score: 79.4% (Distinction)

2002 – 2004 **Higher Secondary Education** (Physics, Chemistry and Biology)

BJB Junior College, Bhubaneswar, Odisha, India

Score: 70.7%

Secondary Education 2002

Port Trust High School, Paradip, Odisha, India

Score: 88.8%

Peer-reviewed publications

- 1. **Sahoo RK***, Manu S, Chandrakumaran NC, Vasudevan K. **2023**. Nuclear and Mitochondrial Genome Assemblies of the Beetle, *Zygogramma bicolorata*, a Globally Important Biocontrol Agent of Invasive Weed *Parthenium hysterophorus*. *Genome Biology and Evolution* 15(10): evad188. 10.1093/gbe/evad188
- 2. Chazot N, Wahlberg N, Freitas AVL, Mitter C, Labandeira C, Sohn J-C, **Sahoo RK**, Seraphim N, de Jong R, Heikkilä M. **2019**. Priors and posteriors in Bayesian timing of divergence analyses: The age of butterflies revisited. *Systematic Biology* 68(5): 797–813. 10.1093/sysbio/syz002
- 3. **Sahoo RK***, Kodandaramaiah U. **2018**. Local host plant abundance explains negative association between larval performance and female oviposition preference in a butterfly. *Biological Journal of the Linnean Society* 125:333–343. 10.1093/biolinnean/bly111
- 4. **Sahoo RK***, Lohman DJ, Wahlberg N, Müller CJ, Brattström O, Collins SC, Peggie D, Aduse-Poku K, Kodandaramaiah U. **2018**. Evolution of *Hypolimnas* butterflies (Nymphalidae): Out-of-Africa origin and *Wolbachia*-mediated introgression. *Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution* 123: 50–58. 10.1016/j.ympev.2018.02.001
- 5. **Sahoo RK***, Warren AD, Collins SC, Kodandaramaiah U. **2017**. Hostplant change and paleoclimatic events explain diversification shifts in skipper butterflies (Family: Hesperiidae). *BMC Evolutionary Biology* 17(1):174. <u>10.1186/s12862-017-1016-x</u>
- 6. **Sahoo RK***, Warren AD, Wahlberg N, Brower AVZ, Lukhtanov VA, Kodandaramaiah U. **2016**. Ten genes and two topologies: an exploration of higher relationships in skipper butterflies. *PeerJ* 4:e2653. 10.7717/peerj.2653
- 7. **Sahoo RK***. **2016**. Why antagonistic traits against cytoplasmic incompatibility are so elusive. *Frontiers in Microbiology* 7:392. <u>10.3389/fmicb.2016.00392</u>

Scientific communications

- 1. **Sahoo RK**. **2017**. Digest: Ancient co-dispersals and host shifts in passerine bird feather mite symbiosis. *Evolution* 71(10):2539–2540. <u>10.1111/evo.13330</u>
- 2. **Sahoo RK** and Kodandaramaiah U. **2017**. Opportunity for diversification: insights from species accumulation pattern in skipper butterflies. *BMC Series blog*.
- 3. **Sahoo RK. 2017**. Gradient in predation risk: indicator of a feedback loop. eLetter to *Science*. http://science.sciencemag.org/content/356/6339/742/tab-e-letters
- 4. **Sahoo RK. 2016**. Letter on "Risks of *Wolbachia* mosquito control". eLetter to *Science*. http://science.sciencemag.org/content/351/6279/1273.2/tab-e-letters
- 5. Mehta P, Kulkarni J, **Sahoo RK**, Arulmalar E, Pawar T and Punjabi G. **2012**. Status and distribution of Malabar giant squirrel (*Ratufa indica*) in Western Ghats of Maharashtra. Wildlife Research and Conservation Society, Pune. Final Technical report submitted to WWF-New Delhi and Rufford Small grants Foundation, United Kingdom.

Selected Awards

2021	Staff Excellence Award Indian Institute of Science Education & Research (IISER) Berhampur, India
2013 – 2017	Junior and Senior Research Fellowships Council of Scientific and Industrial Research (CSIR), India (<i>ca.</i> INR 14,68,000)
2016	International Travel Grant Department of Science and Technology, Govt. of India (INR 1,29,831)
2017	1 st rank in overall performance DST–SERB School on Chemical Ecology National Centre for Biological Sciences (NCBS), Bangalore, India
2016	2 nd runners-up for the poster presentation Ninth International <i>Wolbachia</i> Conference Queensland, Australia
2010	Summer Research Fellowship IAS-INSA-NASI, India (INR 12,000)
2009	Merit scholarship for 1 st rank holder in the P.G. Entrance Exam Pondicherry University, India (INR 2,000)
2006	3 rd rank in the All Orissa Biotech Olympiad Trident Academy of Creative Technology, Bhubaneswar, Odisha, India
2003	Recognition award from District magistrate for among the top positions in High School Certificate Examination 2002, Jagatasinghpur district, Odisha, India

Services and Outreach

Scientific awareness	Interacted with undergraduate/school students from various parts of the state/country during their visit to CCMB/LaCONES (2022-2024)
COVID-19 Test Centre	Participated in sample testing and led the Data management team at IISER Berhampur, India (July - November 2020)
Reviewer assignments	Current Science, PeerJ, Journal of Genetics, Ecology and Evolution, Czech Science Foundation
Membership	International Biogeography Society (2017-18) International Society for Evolution, Medicine and Public Health (2017-18)